Hello.
您好
Take a seat.
坐
How can I help you?
你们什么问题
Marital infidelity.
婚内出轨
You must be
你就是
my five o'clock patient.
约好五点的那个病人吧
What?
啊
Here's your medical history.
这是你的病历
Your name is
叫
Yao Shen.
姚申
It's written here
这上面写着
that you have multiple personality disorder.
你患有多重人格障碍症
That's very rare in our country.
这在咱们国内很少见
It's worth some
这个还是很值得
intensive study.
深入研究的
Now,
现在
we'll chat to all of
咱们跟你体内的
the personalities inside you.
所有人都聊聊吧
OK, let's chat.
聊 聊 聊聊
It's written here that
这上面写着
you have a personality called
你有一重人格叫
Wang Jiajia.
王佳佳
A girl born
一九九零年出生
in Xi'an in 1990.
西安籍的小姑娘
Right, I'm a girl
对 我是来自
from Xi'an.
西安的小女子
When we were dating,
跟你交往那段时间
I was too
我确实太过于以
self-centered.
自我为中心了
I pushed a lot of work
把好多本应该
I should have done myself
我承担的工作
onto you.
都推给了你
I didn't think about it from your perspective.
我也没做到换位思考
I feel like I should apologize to you,
我觉得挺对不起你的
Hao.
小好
Sorry, Hao.
对不起啊 小好
I'm sorry.
对不起
I smacked him in the face,
我直接就是一顿电炮
then I pulled him up
然后拉过来蹦
and kicked him in the butt.
一脚踢他屁股
Then I dragged him over and smacked him.
再拽过来一顿啪啪啪
Wow.
啊
So, just now
所以刚刚
that was Shi Hu,
那个是室虎哥
40-year-old security guard from Northeast China.
四十岁的东北保安
Very interesting.
非常有趣
Hey,
我说
maybe that's enough for today.
要不然今天就算了吧
I, I'm tired, really.
我 我累了 真的
No!
别别别
There's still one more.
还有一位啊
This one's even more interesting.
这位比较有意思
He's called Huang Daxian.
他叫黄大仙
Thank you, doctor.
谢谢医生
Right, Huang Daxian is…
对 黄大仙是
Here.
来了
This old man has calculated,
老夫掐指一算
you'll be met soon with…
你近日必遭
Ma Nan?
马楠
What are you doing here?
你怎么在这儿
There are birds in couples on the trees.
树上的鸟儿成双对
An anxiety disorder?
焦虑症
Right.
是啊
After I broke up with Hao,
跟小好分手后
I discovered
我才发现
I'd been relying on her a lot.
我之前是有多依赖她
When all of the work
所有她之前替
she'd been doing for me
我做的那些工作
all piled
都堆回到
back on me again,
我自己身上的时候
I went crazy.
我整个人都忙疯了
I really can't imagine
我真的完全无法想象
how she took care of
她之前是怎么样一个人
so much work alone before.
处理这么多工作
Not only did she have a lot of work stress,
一方面工作压力大
but actually,
另一方面其实
I've also realized
我也意识到
I was always…
我一直在
Frankly, I was always
说白了我一直
taking advantage of Hao.
在占小好便宜
So I really blamed myself.
所以真的很自责
During that time, I was really
那段时间真的是
anxious and couldn't sleep.
失眠 焦虑
It got progressively worse until now.
一步步发展到了现在
I'm actually seeing a psychiatrist.
居然来看心理医生了
I never thought
没有想到
you'd become like this.
你会变成现在这个样子
It has nothing to do with you.
跟你没关系
It's my problem.
我自己的问题
After that the doctor told me
后来我的医生跟我说
I need to
说你呀
face up to
要正视
the mistakes I'd made,
你之前犯过的错误
so I asked
所以我就麻烦
Hao to come with me
小好陪我来
to this session.
这既是一种治疗手段
It's also a way of me making a break
也算是我对自己的过去
from my past.
做个了断吧
But this is really
但这次真的是
the very last time
最后最后一次
I bother Hao.
麻烦小好了
Sorry for the trouble.
给你添麻烦了
And sorry for worrying you.
也让你担心了
Huh?
啊
Hao didn't tell you
人家小好不告诉你
probably because she was afraid you'd get the wrong idea.
可能就是怕你误会呗
We…
我们
Don't worry. We're fine.
你放心吧 我们没事
Then…
那
I won't bother you two.
我就不打扰你们了
Alright.
好
Take care of yourself.
照顾好自己
Hao.
小好
Goodbye.
再见
Yeah.
嗯
B-Bye.
拜 拜拜
Don't waste your energy explaining.
你就别费劲解释了
If we are just regular friends,
如果我们只是普通朋友
you stalk me
那你又是跟踪
and pretend to be crazy…
又是装疯卖傻的
What was that for?
是为了什么
That's a good question.
这个问题问得好啊
I…
我
Not long ago,
不久之前
someone
有个人
taught me a lesson
他教会了我一个道理
that
那就是
people should live
人应该去过自己
the lives they want to live,
想过的生活
and do the things they want to do,
做自己想做的事
and not worry about what others think.
不要在意别人的眼光
He made me brave and confident
他让我变得勇敢 自信
but when it is the moment
可到了需要他勇敢
he needs to be brave,
面对的时候
he hesitates.
他又变得犹犹豫豫
Honestly,
老实说
I'm a little disappointed.
这让我有点失望
That guy's just like that.
这个人就是这样
Strict on others, lenient on himself.
严于律人 宽于律己
He should fix that.
那这可要改呀
He will.
改 会改的
Fix it quick.
快点改
Hurry up.
快走快走
- We two are so close. - Look…
咱俩挨着呢你看
Over here.
老师这边
How are they taking so long
他们怎么换个衣服
to change clothes?
这么久啊
They're probably
大概 他们是想
using this time
利用这个时间
to go through their points again.
再捋一捋论点吧
But why am I
但我怎么总是觉得
so flustered?
那么心慌呢
Don't worry, Hao.
小好姐 放心吧
We'll definitely win.
我们一定会赢的
But, looking at these points,
可是 我看这论点
I keep thinking it's too unpredictable.
总觉得变数太大了
Here they are.
来了
Hello.
你们好
Welcome
欢迎大家来到
to today's "Xingyuan"
今天的行远杯
Tripartite Debate
三方辩论大赛的
competition.
比赛现场
Let me first introduce
让我们先来认识一下
each of the debaters.
各方辩友
Firstly, Team A is
首先是我们的甲方
Team 235.
二三五辩论队
Their motion is
他们的持方是
"In life,
人生路上
first you must learn to go for it".
先要学会拿得起
Let's give them a big welcome.
让我们欢迎他们
Hello everyone.
大家好
I am the commentator of
我是本场比赛的
this debate, Lao Xu.
辩论解说老徐
I'm Dalong.
我是大龙
Today we'll be
今天由我们
commentating on this
为芒果干视频
competition for
平台的用户
Dry Mango Video users.
带来这场比赛的解说
Right now, we introduce Team B.
现在正在介绍的是乙方
The steady as a rock
这个常年稳如泰山的
Nanxiang Technical School team.
南翔技校代表队
Their motion today is
他们今天的持方是
"Let go".
放得下
And lastly, Team C.
最后这个丙方呢
They have been a star in the debate circle
则是这两年圈子里的
for the past two years.
一支明星队
They just merged into
他们刚刚合并成为
the new DUFE Team.
新的东财大的辩论队
Their motion is "Leave it to fate".
持方是随缘
This motion,
这个持方啊
hearing it, I feel like
听上去我感觉就
there's a problem there.
有一点问题
Because it appears to make sense,
因为它好像很有道理
but doesn't actually have any points.
但是没有什么点
Right.
没错
Next, let's begin
下面让我们进入
with the speeches.
申论环节
We'll start with the first team.
我们先从甲方开始
Each side has three minutes
每方共有三分钟的
for their speeches.
申论时间
Any debater can speak.
可由任意辩手发言
After 30 seconds of one side speaking
一方申论三十秒后
the other two teams
其余两方
can ring the bell to express disagreement
皆可按铃表示异议
and contend for the right to speak first and
争夺优先申论权
proceed with their speech.
并接续发言
This will continue until the time runs out.
直到时间用尽
If two sides ring the bell at the same time
若两方同时按铃
or no side rings the bell,
或没人按铃
Team A, B and C
则按照顺位
will speak in order of A, B, and C.
甲 乙 丙发言
Now the competition begins.
现在比赛正式开始
Hello everyone,
大家好
firstly, let's talk about
首先我们来理解
this debate topic.
一下这个辩题
What does "go for it" mean?
什么是拿得起
Is it a description of
是对我们能力的
our abilities?
一种描述
I can do this.
拿得起这个
I can do that?
拿得起那个吗
Obviously not.
显然不是
The true meaning of "going for it"
拿得起的真正含义
is being brave enough to go for it.
是敢于拿起
In life, going for it
人生路上的拿得起
is being brave enough to take on and challenge
就是敢于承担与挑战
and chase the things you want
敢于去追求自己想要
to chase.
追求的一切
Think about it, in our lives,
想一下这一路上
aren't there so many
不正是有那么多
honors, duties
你想拿起的荣耀
and responsibilities you want to go for?
责任和义务
This allows us to
才让我们在
overcome all of the obstacles
如此漫长的人生道路上
on the road of life
披荆斩棘
that led up here today.
走到了今天
In the face of difficulties,
那面对难题
we must keep going for it
我要一道道拿起来
to solve them.
去解开它
The first time on the debating stage,
第一次上台打辩论
I have to get up there and not be afraid of embarrassing myself.
要走上去不怕丢脸
As my parents slowly grow old,
当父母渐渐老去
I have to take the responsibilities of my family.
我们要拿起家庭的责任
When faced with love,
面对爱情
I must have the courage
我们一定要鼓起勇气
to go for it,
去追求
instead of giving into
而不是屈服于
my fears
自己的恐惧
or avoiding it, thinking I'll leave it to fate, to
用随缘之类的逃避行为
make excuses for my mediocrity.
为自己的平庸寻找借口
Thank you.
谢谢
That's the point.
就是这个点
Hey.
哎
That point.
这 这是个点啊
That's a wise point, friends.
朋友们 这是个知识点
The first debater from Team A intentionally
甲方一辩故意卖了个
exposed a flaw
破绽给丙方
for Team C.
让他接招
That was very smart.
这个非常有想法
Once Team C steals the floor,
但是一旦丙方抢发言
Team B will go next
第三个发言的乙方
and they're bound to refute
势必来反驳
Team C as their opening statement.
丙方来开场
Then in the first round of speeches,
那第一轮申论
the focus will be shifted
当中被集中火力的
from Team A to Team C.
就从甲方转移到了丙方
So the tactic
所以说这个战术
choice is critical.
选择非常关键
If they don't steal the floor, there'll be trouble.
如果不抢就麻烦了
Come on.
来呀
Team B has taken the floor.
乙方抢发言成功
They wanted to trick us?
想套路我们
Nice try.
没那么容易
Team A told us that in life,
甲方辩友告诉我们
you have to keep forging ahead and struggling,
人生要进取 要奋斗
you have to strive hard to get
要努力争取自己
everything you want.
所要的一切
That's all true.
这都没有错
But they're using a straw man argument.
但是 他们在偷换概念
In summary, it's that life
总结一下就是人生
is about constantly
需要不断地去得到
going for it, as you say,
而你们所谓的拿得起
in order to get more.
都是为了得到更多
But must we go for everything
可是我们应该拿起所有
and take it all?
得到一切吗
My opponent,
对方辩友
your name is greed.
您的名字叫贪婪
Impressive.
好厉害
All of a sudden, the mood
一下子就把情绪都
has changed.
化解掉了
She's trying to win them over with a soft approach.
她这是以柔克刚啊
And getting everything isn't really
而且得到真的不是一件
an easy thing to do.
容易的事情
"I long to return, riding the wind high,
我欲乘风归去
yet, of the jade mansions I'm afraid so".
又恐琼楼玉宇的担忧
"If we despair in our lifetime of all affairs,
人生在世不称意
tomorrow let us sail away with loosened hair".
明朝散发弄扁舟的
These poems
诗意
are all about facing the helplessness
写满的 是面对人生
and bitterness of all those things
想得而不可得的
in life we want but can't have.
无奈与辛酸
Is gaining
得到
the norm in life?
是人生的常态吗
No, losing is the norm in life.
不 人生的常态是失去
We're always losing things.
我们一直在失去
Losing time. Losing opportunities.
失去时间 失去机会
Losing the people we love.
失去我们所爱的人
And life makes us
而人生就是要让我们
experience anguish and difficulty
在这样反复地失去当中
in the midst of all this repeated loss.
去体会那份苦恼与困顿
So,
所以
we need to learn to let go.
我们必须学会放下
It's the only way we can
学会放下我们才
put our limited
能够把自己
energy and resources
有限的精力和资源
towards the more important
转移到人生更重要的
choices in life.
抉择当中来
Then we'll know
我们才知道
what are things we must go for,
什么应该拿得起
what is worth daring to go for.
什么值得勇于拿得起
Then we'll have the power
我们才有力量
to face this world.
面对这个世界
Team A's proposition of going for it
甲方同学主张拿得起
was inspiring.
催人奋进
Team B's argument of letting go
乙方同学表达放得下
was thought-provoking.
引人深思
However, today our side's position is:
而今天我方的观点是
"Leave it to fate".
随缘
It seems like we should just go ahead
看上去我似乎应该直接
and sit back down.
坐下
Win or lose, we'll just leave it to fate.
至于输赢 随缘就好
That's right.
没错
No.
不对呀
But if I just sit and wait for the results,
可如果我坐等结果
that's not leaving it to fate,
这不叫随缘
that's giving up, right?
这叫放弃 对吗
Aside from religious interpretation,
抛除宗教体系下的诠释
we believe
我们认为
leaving it to fate isn't about not making a choice,
随缘不是不去做出选择
it's about not forcing one.
而是不去强行做出选择
Adapting to the time and place,
因时因地 随机应变
that's really leaving it to fate.
才是真正的随缘
It's a wise philosophy for life.
才是有智慧的生活哲学
Just like if I want to eat braised pork,
就好像我想吃红烧肉
but the cafeteria only has fried vegetables
可是食堂只剩地三鲜
and Kung Pao chicken left.
和宫保鸡丁了
Team A would drive ten kilometers
甲方辩友打车十公里
to eat at a restaurant,
去饭店吃
wasting time and money.
消耗时间与钱财
Team B would tell themselves to
乙方辩友告诉自己
let it go,
罢了罢了
but in their heart,
但心里总归是
they'd be a little disappointed.
有些失落怅然的
However our side believes
而我方认为
on the long road of life,
在漫长的人生道路上
we must first learn to
我们首先要学会的
choose whichever is better between
就是在地三鲜和鸡丁中
the fried vegetables
去选择口味
and Kung Pao chicken
还行的那一个
and accept this choice.
并且接受这样的选择
When you learn to leave it to fate
当你学会随缘
you won't
你既不会因为
run out of energy
太想得到
from wanting too much
而耗尽心力
or become despondent from
也不会因为被迫放弃
being forced to give up.
而怅然若失
It's a delicate balance
现实与理想
between realism and idealism,
得到了精妙的平衡
because now you
因为此刻的你
understand the most important
明白了最重要的
principle.
一个道理
It depends on the circumstances.
具体情况具体分析
Do what you can in the circumstances.
做特定条件下能做的事
This is the proper philosophy for life.
这是人生真正的方法论
She beat down both the attacks
她同时攻赢了
from Team A and B in one blow!
甲乙两方
Right, usually,
对 一般来说啊
in the first round of speeches,
在申论第一轮
everyone will focus on
大家都会集中地
refuting one side
反驳某一方
to create a partial advantage.
来形成局部优势
But with DUFE debating this way…
但是东财这么玩 那
Aren't they just making trouble for themselves?
岂不是给自己找麻烦
Or are they just too confident?
或者就是太自信了
Should we try to take the floor?
抢不抢
Ma Nan.
马楠
Wait.
等一下
Do you think they should go for it?
你觉得应该抢吗
I don't think they will.
我觉得他们不会抢
Team C is antagonizing everyone.
一队现在这么树敌
The best method is to exploit the victory
最好的办法是扩大战果
and let Team B and C go first.
让乙方丙方先阐述
We should go for
我们现在要争取
the final spot to do the speech to
最后一个发言
consolidate our advantage in this section.
巩固环节优势
So today,
因此今天
our viewpoint is
我方的观点是
that in life we must first
人生路上先要
learn to leave it to fate.
学会随缘
Thank you.
谢谢
We just said,
我方刚才说过了
the norm in life is loss,
人生的常态是失去
and with your side's leaving it to fate
而对于您方的随缘来讲
an important prerequisite is
一个重要的先决条件
if fate doesn't allow me something,
就是缘不予我
I give up.
我便放下
In your example of the
在您方红烧肉的
braised pork,
例子中
our side also argued to
我方不也正是放下了
let go of that pork that we
心头对于红烧肉的
craved, didn't we?
执念
And make rational choice
把理性投注于
between the options.
眼下的选项中
Only then, you can go with your
才有了您方口中的
"it depends on the situation"?
具体情况具体分析吗
So this is our first point.
所以这是第一点
Letting go is a prerequisite.
放得下是先决条件
Team B is focusing their attack on Team C.
乙方重点打了丙方
Now's the time to act.
现在是出手的时候了
Why?
为什么
Shouldn't they let those two
不应该是那两边
tear each other apart?
互相撕吗
If they give this chance
如果这个机会
to Team C,
让给一队
it'd be easy for them to make
他们很轻松就可以
a rebuttal.
防守反击
Stealing the floor is basically
抢了申论就等于
stealing the points of Team C.
抢了一队的分
Get it?
明白吗
Got it.
明白了
My opponent said
对方辩友说
letting go is a prerequisite of
放得下是拿得起
going for it.
的先决条件
But if I
可是如果我
can't go for anything,
什么都拿不起
what do I have to let go of?
该放下什么呢
If my hands are empty,
两手空空
am I letting go of thin air?
放下的是空气吗
If we're hesitating at the
当我们站在起点
starting line,
彷徨的时候
let's take a look
不妨我们去看看
at life's finish line.
人生的终点
Imagine,
试想一下
in the twilight of our life, on our deathbed,
暮年时分 弥留之际
what are the things
真正让我们可以
that can make us calm
从容地离去
and we can let go of?
可以放下的到底是什么
It's after we've achieved our dreams,
是我们拿起梦想后
the trophies filling up the shelf,
那满墙的荣誉
it's after we've taken on responsibilities,
是我们拿起责任后
the grandchildren filling up the house.
如今的儿孙满堂
Only if we keep
是我们人生路上
going for it again and again,
一次又一次的拿起
will we have these memories to look back on
才有我们回忆青春时候
and that true serenity.
那一份份沉甸甸的安详
Life is like
人生就像是一场
beating a game.
通关游戏
Some of the levels are really hard.
有的关卡真的很难很难
There are tough enemies that can
有的敌人也血厚防高
kill you in one hit.
甚至对你一击必杀
What should we do?
你怎么办呢
Team B says let it go.
乙方辩友说 放下吧
You can drop the game.
那这游戏你不打便是
Team C would say to leave it to fate.
丙方辩友说 随缘就好了
If you can't beat it, you can't beat it.
打不过就是打不过
But,
可是
I want to look at
我就是想去看一看
the view in the next level,
下一关的风景
because I know
因为我知道
it's there.
它就在那里
Liu Yanze, take it if you have the guts.
刘彦泽 有种就接招
Team A presented
甲方辩手举了一个
a very interesting example of
很有趣的例子
playing a game.
打游戏
As a player,
作为玩家
you can, of course, choose
你当然可以选择
to fight an enemy to the death.
跟一个敌人死磕到底
But as a child, a parent,
但作为子女 父母
an employee, a boss?
职员 老板呢
Can we really
我们真的可以
keep fighting, no matter what?
不顾一切地去死磕吗
Is it really possible to
这世间种种的一切
go for or to let go of
会因为我想要拿起
everything
而拿起
as I please in this world?
想要放下就能够放下吗
Then there wouldn't be things we can't go for or can't let go of.
那又何来求不得而放不下呢
We must make the best of the situation.
随遇而安 因势利导
"Grow beans beneath the southern mountains".
种豆南山下
"Do not be pleased by your gains, or saddened by your losses".
不以物喜己悲
That's not passivity.
这才不是人生的消极
It's the wisdom of survival.
而是生存的智慧
He's confusing objective principles
把遵循客观规律
with leaving things to fate.
混淆成随缘
Shame on him.
太不要脸了
"Grow beans beneath the southern mountains."
种豆南山下的
Tao Yuanming is all well and good.
陶渊明也好
"Do not be pleased by your gains, or saddened by your losses."
不以物喜己悲的
Fan Zhongyan, too.
范仲淹也罢
But aren't they
这本就与我们
different from our
少年的心境
adolescent state of mind?
是不一样的 对吧
Young people are empty-handed.
年轻人两手空空
They want to develop, to build,
想要去开拓 去创造
to take the things that they want,
去拿起他们想要
to take it all.
得到的一切
This is normal.
这很正常
Is Team B supporting us?
乙方这是要联刘抗曹吗
Isn't he
这不就在
supporting our point of view?
赞同我方观点吗
They used our idea
他们利用了我们的观点
first to object and
先做反驳
make a rebuttal,
一来做了驳论
then drive a wedge between us
二来挑拨了我们
and Team C.
跟一队的关系
They're just
这就是在给
putting pressure on us.
咱们戴高帽了
They've definitely got another trick up their sleeve.
肯定还留了一手
But do the desires of life
可是人生的欲望
have no finish line?
就没有终点吗
We hate not getting what we want.
我们痛恨得不到
We hate not being able to pursue what we want.
也厌恶求不得
I stayed up all night studying,
挑灯夜读
why couldn't I get into
为什么我就不能考
the university I wanted to?
上心仪的大学
I starve myself to get thin,
减肥挨饿
why haven't I lost
为什么我的体重
any weight at all?
依然不动如山
Don't we deserve to
难道付出之后
be rewarded for our efforts?
就不应该得到回报吗
Do you see?
看到了吗
Your spirit will collapse.
心态崩了
Look, I was right.
你看吧 我没说错吧
If you say that going for it
如果说 拿得起
helps us constantly
是在不断地构建
build our lives,
我们的人生
it's addition.
是加量
Then letting go
那么放得下
is stripping life
就是在剥离
of unnecessary things.
人生的不值得
It's subtraction.
是减法
This kind of stripping away and letting go
这种剥离 这一句放下
helps our lives become
让我们的人生变得
simpler and purer.
简单而纯粹
It helps us to possess beauty of individuality.
让我们拥有了个性之美
But most importantly,
但最重要的
it helps us see clearly
是它让我们看清楚了
what exactly is
什么才是真正的
important to us.
人间值得
Thank you.
谢谢
Team B took the initiative to get to
乙方主动抢了
speak first in the last round.
最后一轮抢先发言
Isn't that bad for them?
那不吃亏吗
You know,
大家知道
in tripartite debate,
在这个三方的赛制之下
contending for speeches
对于申论的争夺
gets very intense.
非常激烈
The most important
其中最重要的
thing is
一个点就是
who gets to go last
能不能最后一个发言
and sum up what their opponents have said.
来总结对方
So in previous competitions,
所以在以前的比赛当中
there have been times when
最后一轮也出现过
no one contends.
没人抢的这种情况
Then they're in trouble.
就 就开天窗了嘛
That's trouble,
开天窗
but Team B was right
但是乙方第一个选择
to do the speech first.
发言是对的
If you're the second last
如果倒数第二个人发言
to speak,
的情况下
that's the worst.
就是最惨的
Right now what's crucial
所以现在最关键的
is whether
这个点
Team C steals the floor
就是丙方会不会
to make a rebuttal on Team B
为了报复
and get revenge.
和反驳乙方去抢发言
Plan failed.
计划失败
Hello everyone.
大家好
We might as well
咱们不妨就着
follow Team B's speech
乙方辩友刚才的发言
by saying
接着说
have we young people
我们年轻人真的是
really overburdened
把自己的人生
our lives with
加码到了不堪
weighty responsibilities?
重负的地步了吗
It doesn't seem like it.
好像不是吧
In the rapidly developing world of today.
在飞速发展的今天
young people, one after another,
一个又一个年轻人
keep saying "whatever"
把都行 可以
"sure" and "it doesn't matter".
没关系挂在嘴边
Meaning, worth, dreams, hopes,
意义 价值 梦想 期望
are things that they avoid,
这些都成了他们避而
words they don't talk about.
不谈的词汇
And then they feel satisfied
然后缩起来
curled up in their corners.
获得角落里的满足
In Japan,
在日本
this means low-desire society.
这是低欲望社会
In the West, this is a lost generation.
在欧美 这是失落的一代
Cynicism rules. There is no longer any meaning.
犬儒当道 意义不再
Young people are giving up.
年轻人都在放下
They're all leaving it to fate.
都在随缘
So who's going for it?
那么又有谁在拿起呢
So, you're right,
所以没错
our point of view means
我们的观点就是要去
always going for more.
得到更多
We will throw ourselves
在事业上我们就
into our careers.
是要入仕
In love,
在感情上
we want to jump in headfirst.
我们渴望入红尘
We'll go out into the world to find our fortune.
在财富上我们要敢下海
That's our perspective.
这 就是我们的观点
Because today's world
因为在今天的世界里
still needs every one of us
依旧需要我们每一个人
to have the skills, duties and responsibilities,
有能力 有责任 有担当
to go for it.
拿得起
Thank you.
谢谢
Not bad.
不错
What we're discussing today
我们今天讨论的
are attitudes to life.
是面对人生的态度
Team A said to want more.
甲方辩友说要丰满
Our lives are about
我们的人生
addition.
是加量
Team B said
乙方辩友说
letting go is a kind of stripping.
放得下是一种剥离
When the unnecessary are stripped away,
剥离掉不值得
life has meaning.
人生才值得
It's about concentration.
是浓缩
It's like the question of whether it's better
这就好比喝一碗海鲜汤
to have a huge portion of seafood soup
到底是量大料足更重要
or one that's delicious and beautifully presented?
还是味道鲜美更关键呢
The answer is,
答案是
it depends on if we're hungry.
要看我饿不饿了
If one day I'm tired,
如果我累了一天
and my belly is grumbling,
饥肠辘辘
then volume is
那肯定是量大料足
more important.
更重要
But if I have a date with a girl,
可是如果我约了女生
and I carefully prepared,
精心去赴约
then its flavor and appearance become
那貌似美味醇厚要排在
paramount.
首位了
After all, if I take my dates to
毕竟在量大料足的
a food stall that serves big portions,
地摊上约会的话
it'd be easy for me to stay single forever.
是很容易万年单身的
Leaving it to fate is not a passive life.
随缘并非是消极度日
It's not about just getting by.
也绝不是得过且过
If you know what's just right for the situation
懂得什么是恰到好处
then you can make
才能在纷扰的生活中
every day part of
把每一天
a wonderful life amidst the
都过成精彩人生的
chaos of this world.
一部分
Thank you.
谢谢
We still don't know what
也不知道他们现在
their score is now.
分数怎么样
I have a way.
我有办法
So?
怎么样
We're at 18 points.
我们十八分
Team C has 17.
一队十七分
We have one more than them!
我们比他们多一分哪
Liu Yanze isn't targeting us.
刘彦泽没有针对我们
I'm not surprised.
也不意外
Although the tactic failed,
虽然战术没有得逞
at least we're still ahead in the scores.
但毕竟分数还是领先的
We got the opening down.
开场我们总算拿下来了
We'll see what happens in the rebuttal.
就看接下来攻辩了
This part is more about strategy.
这个环节更看策略
Thank you to our three teams for
感谢三方辩手的
their excellent speeches.
精彩申论
Sure enough, during the first section,
果然在这第一个环节
they've all been going head-to-head
已经针锋相对
against each other.
环环相扣了呢
So next up is our
那么接下来就是我们的
rebuttal section.
攻辩环节
This time we'll begin with Team A.
这次从甲方先开始
Choose any team
任意选择一方
or two teams to do the rebuttal.
或者两方进行攻辩
There will be three rounds, each one two minutes.
共三轮 每轮两分钟
Go ahead, Team A.
有请甲方辩手
Xiaoyu will choose Team C.
小鱼会选一队
I choose Team C.
我选择丙方辩友
Again.
又来了
Hello, my opponent.
对方辩友 您好
Hello.
您好
Between leaving it to fate and going for it,
随缘和拿起
which one is more likely
哪一个更有可能
to get us love?
让我们得到爱情呢
What does your side think?
那您方认为呢
Going for it, obviously.
当然是拿得起
Those who are willing to bravely chase after love
面对真爱勇敢直追的人
are the ones who deserve it, right?
才配拥有爱情 不是吗
Yin Nan can turn the attack
殷楠一句话就转
around in one sentence!
守为攻了
How did Xiaoyu get it in her way again?
这小鱼怎么又着道了
But it's no good if you force it.
可是强扭的瓜不甜哪
What's the use of
光有拿得起的勇气
courage alone?
有什么用呢
I said that we must first go for it.
我说的是先得拿得起
Whether it works
能成不能成
obviously depends on whether the two people
当然还得看这俩人
are compatible or not.
合适不合适了
Compatibility is important, of course.
合适当然重要
But sometimes people who are compatible
可有时候合适的人
are millions of miles apart,
远隔千山万水
and maybe not able to meet.
未必碰得到啊
If you can't meet them,
碰都碰不到
then does your problem
那您方的问题
not exist at all?
是不是根本不存在呢
When two compatible people
合适的两个人又恰好
just happen to meet,
碰到了一起
what do we usually
我们一般管这种情况叫
call that?
什么呢
We call it…
叫
Fate, right?
叫缘分 对不对
So doesn't fate come first,
所以说拿得起
before we can go for it?
是不是在缘分之后呢
She fell for it again.
又进套了
Déjà vu.
似曾相识
Get used to it.
习惯就好
That's fine.
没关系
Let's go to the next question.
我们继续下一个问题
What do you think is the essence
您认为拿得起的
of going for it?
本质是什么
It's a can-do attitude.
一种敢于尝试的态度
But I don't know what the essence of
但不知道随缘的
leaving it to fate is.
本质是什么
The essence of leaving it to fate is
随缘的本质是
not assuming anything.
不预设立场
If going for it is bravely trying something,
如果拿得起是敢于尝试
then are all things you can try
那么是不是所有的尝试
worthy of encouragement?
都是值得鼓励的呢
No.
不是
But I believe that in the face
但我认为面对
of all life's opportunities,
人生的可能性
bravely trying something is a good thing.
勇于尝试总是好的
What if this opportunity is
如果这种可能性是
something bad?
一种恶呢
So it depends
所以要看
on what the opportunity is, right?
是什么可能性嘛
Before the opportunity appears
所以可能性出现之前
there's no way to try it, right?
是无法尝试的 对吗
So?
那又怎么样呢
That's exactly what my side said,
那就是我方所说的
not making assumptions,
不预设立场
leaving it to fate.
也就是随缘
Thank you.
谢谢
Next is Team B's turn
下面有请乙方
for the rebuttal.
辩手进行攻辩
You also have two minutes.
同样为两分钟
Please.
有请乙方辩手
I choose Team C.
我选择丙方辩友
How do leaving it to fate and letting go
请问随缘和放得下的
differ?
区别在哪里
Letting go
放下
is about immediately resigning yourself
是才下眉头又上心头的
to something.
无可奈何
Leaving it to fate is the surprise when "there seems no road beyond,
随缘是山重水复疑无路
and among the willows and flowers another village appears".
柳暗花明又一村的惊喜
OK, then please tell me
好 那么再请问
if Xiaoming doesn't do well in a test,
小明考试没考好
and tells himself, "it's fine,
安慰自己说没关系
I'll leave the score to fate,"
多少分随缘吧
how is that different from letting it go?
这跟放得下有什么区别
Xiaoming is only burying
小明只是把头
his head in the sand.
埋进沙子里
Do you think
难道您方认为
letting go and deceiving yourself
放得下与自欺欺人
are the same thing?
是一个意思吗
I understand…
我理解
It doesn't seem like it.
好像也不是吧
In the same way,
同样的
leaving it to fate is about
随缘是关注于
making the best decision
现有条件下
in the circumstances.
做出最优解
If Xiaoming hadn't deceived himself,
如果小明没有自欺欺人
and chosen to accept his current
而是选择接受失败的
failure,
现实
and thought he had a better
并觉得自己有提高的
chance to
可能
plan out his future studies, that
制定后面的学习计划
would be leaving it to fate.
这个 才叫随缘
I understand what your side means by leaving it to fate,
我理解您方所谓的随缘
it's to make us
就是让我们
react without
没有任何的情绪
any emotion and from a
只是纯粹客观地
purely objective standpoint.
做出反应嘛
No, it's about reason.
不对 是理性
Leaving it to fate isn't without emotion,
随缘既不是没有感情
and it's not driven by pure emotion either.
也不是纯粹感性
It's about using reason to analyze situations
而是用理性分析情况
and make choices.
做出选择
Ma Nan.
马楠
I suddenly thought of a problem.
我突然意识到一个问题
What problem?
什么问题
Team C's point.
一队的立论
What's wrong?
怎么了
Team C's argument is so simple that
一队的立论简单到
apart from the definition, they have no points.
除了定义没有论点
Their definition of leaving it to fate
他们的定义随缘
is not assuming anything.
就是不预设立场
To judge according to the circumstances.
具体问题具体分析
And their point
而他们的论点
is precisely that
恰恰就是具体问题
adapting to circumstances
具体分析
is the best philosophy
才是人生的最重
in life.
要方法论
That's…
这
So sly of them.
太奸诈了
I'll do it.
我来吧
Maybe I should do it.
还是我来吧
I'm more familiar with the argument structure.
我对立论框架更熟悉
I'll do it.
我来吧
OK.
好
Next is the final round of inquiries.
下面是最后一轮质询
Go ahead, Team C.
有请丙方辩手
I want to rebut
我要对甲方
Team A and Team B.
以及乙方辩友进行攻辩
No way!
不是吧
Is that against the rules?
这个规则 可以吗
It's not.
可以是可以
But, it's very rare.
但是 太少见了
Team A and B are likely
甲乙双方很可能
to come together to
一起联合起来
refute Team C.
对抗丙方
Right, this will be fun.
对 没错 太会玩了
Viewers,
观众朋友们
today's competition
今天我们这场比赛
is great value for money.
绝对是物超所值
Amazing!
精彩极了
So, please scan the QR code
所以 欢迎观众朋友们
on the screen and
扫描屏幕当中的二维码
become a Dry Mango Video member.
加入芒果干视频会员
There's a 20% discount right now.
现在扫描还有八折优惠
Team A,
请问甲方
is it possible to go for
人生中所有东西都
everything in life?
能拿得起吗
My side means that you must
我方的意思是
first go for something to be able to let it go
只有拿起才有放下
and leave it to fate,
和随缘
so most things are like that.
所以 大部分是这样的
Team B,
再请问乙方
is it possible to let everything go?
是不是一切皆可放下
It's not.
也不是
My side is saying we must first learn to let go
我方是说先要学会放下
in order to face life better.
才能更好地面对生活
Then, Team A,
那请问甲方
how can you go for the letting go
如何拿起乙方口中
Team B describes?
的放下
Team B, how can you let go of
乙方又如何放下
the going for it that Team A describes?
甲方口中的拿起呢
That's simple,
很简单
my side would just go for
乙方放下的
Team B's letting go.
我方拿起就好了
So Team A's going for it is wrong.
所以甲方的拿起就错了
My side is also trying to convince them
我方也是要劝他们
to learn to let go.
学会放下嘛
But life is often about going for something
可人生经常是拿起
and letting go.
和放下
There appears to be no space for your side's
这里好像没有你方
leaving it to fate.
随缘什么事吧
My side agrees with this perspective.
这个观点我方同意
In this round, why don't we two
不如这个环节就我们
go against each other,
两方交锋
and Team C just leave it to fate?
丙方随缘就好嘛
I'm sure both sides have heard before
我相信两位都听说过
the story of Sisyphus.
西西弗斯的故事吧
He was punished by the gods
他被众神惩罚
to push a huge rock up a mountain,
推着一块巨石走向山顶
but as soon as the rock reached the top
可是巨石一到山顶
it would slide back down the mountain,
就会再次滑落回山底
endlessly going back and forth
在拿起和放下间
between going for it and letting go,
周而复始
just like what Team A and B agreed.
正如甲乙双方的共识
Are you sure this painful life
难道这样痛苦的人生
is what we're pursuing?
就是我们的追求吗
That's just your opinion.
这只是您方一家之言
Camus's play
在加谬的戏剧
"Sisyphus"
西西弗斯中
criticizes this kind of
就批判了您这种
nihilistic attitude.
否则努力的虚无主义
And like Sisyphus,
而像西西弗斯这样
fighting against the
敢于对命运的悲剧
tragedies of fate and
和生命的荒谬
absurdities of life.
进行反抗
That in itself gives life
本身就赋予了生命
a noble value.
崇高的价值
Why must our lives be
我们的人生为何一上来
so tragic?
就要如此悲怆呢
Is living a normal life
过好普通人的生活
necessarily cowardice?
难道就是一种怯懦吗
So Team B rejects this moral abduction.
所以乙方拒绝道德绑架
Team A doesn't want
甲方则不想让
young people to give up fighting.
年轻人放弃奋斗
So actually
所以其实
both sides are
您两方一同告诉
telling us
我们的就是
that leaving it to fate is the best
对于大多数年轻人而言
choice for most young people.
随缘才是最好的选择
Right?
对吗
No, because…
不对 因为
Amazing!
太精彩了
He did a rebuttal on both sides,
故意把攻辩打成一打二
and still won.
居然还赢了
To be honest,
这个咱们有一说一啊
I've seen thousands of debates,
我看过几千场比赛
but I've never seen this before.
从来都没有见过
The advantages of their speeches have been levelled.
申论的优势都被拉平了
And the inquiry strategy of this round
而且整轮质询策略上
was totally lost to the other side.
都输给对方了
We're at 16 points.
我们十六分
Team C has 18 points.
一队十八分
Team B has 14.
乙方十四分
It all rests on the free debate.
就看自由辩论了
That's fine, we just need to keep steady.
没事 要稳住
Next we'll move into the
接下来让我们进入到
nerve-wracking and intense
紧张刺激的
free debate section.
自由辩论环节
In this section each team
该环节每队发言
will speak for three minutes.
时间为三分钟
Each side can speak freely
各方辩友自由发言
until their time runs out.
直到时间用尽
First, we'll ask Team B
首先我们有请乙方辩友
to begin. Please.
有请
Zhuangzi said: "It's a thing,
庄子云 其为物
that accompanies all others,
无不将也
when they are overthrown
无不迎也 无不成也
and obtain completion.
无不毁也
It's tranquility,
其名撄宁
amid all disturbances,
撄宁也者
that lead to its perfection".
撄而后成者也
My opponents,
对方辩友
isn't this a kind
这是不是一种
of higher realm?
更高的境界呢
My opponent,
对方辩友
please use modern Chinese
请您用现代汉语
to translate.
翻译翻译
Is a translation needed?
还需要翻译吗
According to your opinion, you can
按照您方的观点
leave it to fate whether you understand or not.
懂不懂随缘就好
Starting off with Zhuangzi.
上来就庄子啊
It didn't get much of a reaction from the audience.
这回观众反应不过来
Maybe they slipped up.
可能要栽啊
A good debater perhaps shouldn't
辩手没事掉书袋
rely too much on literary quotes.
不是没辙就是菜
The higher the realm
越高的境界越是
the longer it takes to reach.
要慢慢修炼
Hasn't my opponent forgotten
对方辩友不要忘了
that our debate question is how
我们的辩题是先要
we should
如何
live the first
讲的就是人生的
part of our lives?
起步阶段啊
You're saying we shouldn't
您方口口声声说着不要
assume too much,
预设太多
but also ask everyone to assume
可是又要大家预设一个
an attitude-less attitude.
没有态度的态度
Aren't you
您方是不是太自相
self-contradictory?
矛盾了点啊
A double negative means a yes,
双重否定就是肯定嘛
my fellow debater.
对方辩友
Zhuangzi's philosophy is to recover one's original simplicity.
庄子的哲学是返璞归真
Why can't this become
这为什么不能成为
our guide to life?
我们的人生指导呢
Isn't Mencius's "I go against thousands"
孟子的虽千万人吾往矣
a kind of go-for-it
是不是一种拿得起的
attitude?
态度呢
The Confucianism of Confucius and Mencius
孔孟的儒学统治
ruled in China for two thousand years.
中国两千年
May I ask what Zhuangzi's theory
敢问庄子的学说
was doing then?
在干嘛呢
Isn't Mencius's bravery
孟子的敢勇
based upon letting go
难道不正是建立在
of one's own fame and fortune
放下了自身功名利禄
and even life itself?
乃至生命的前提下吗
That's still letting go first, right?
还是放下在先 对不对
According to what Team B says,
按照乙方辩友的说法
daring to move forward is
敢于向前就是
letting go of what's behind you.
放下了向后
Daring to work hard
敢于努力就是
is letting go of comfort.
放下了安逸
So going for it is always
那是不是所有拿得起
letting go in disguise?
都是变相地放不下
Then can we say that
那我可不可以这么说
letting go is also
所有放得下都是
going for it?
拿得起呢
So stop fighting, you two.
所以您两方也别吵了
Leaving it to fate leads.
随缘才是第一位的
Like finding a partner,
比如找对象
isn't it mostly about fate?
是不是就主要看缘分呢
She's so cocky. She's asking for a fight.
自找群殴啊 这么嚣张
My fellow debater,
对方辩友
today we're talking about
今天我们聊的是
the big things in life,
人生大事
please don't get hung up on things like
请不要纠结于找对象
finding a partner.
这种事情好不好
If you don't find a partner,
如果不找对象
your genes will end
您的基因就要终结于
with you.
您这一生了
My fellow debater,
对方辩友
you might not know that
您可能不知道
the ratio of men to women in China
中国男女比例为
is 117 to 100.
一百一十七比一百
That means for every
也就是说每一百
117 men
一十七个男性
17 of them will be single.
有十七个都是光棍
My opponent, you leave it to fate,
对方辩友 您随缘
and you'll be alone!
您光棍啊
I think that makes a lot of sense.
我觉得 很有道理
Going for it is a kind of trying something.
拿得起是一种尝试
If you never try, you'll never know.
凡事你不试怎么知道呢
If everything must be
如果所有事情都要
tried once,
试一遍
my opponent probably needs
对方辩友可能需要
another 500 years to do it.
向天再借五百年了
Who has that many opportunities
人生哪儿来那么多
for trials and errors in their lives?
试错的机会呢
I have a friend who
我的一个朋友
used to be very afraid
之前非常恐惧
of the 800-meter running test.
八百米体测
But when she finally
可是当她最终
went for it,
勇敢地拿起来
she was able to pass it.
却发现成功通过
What's wrong with pushing
人生路上逼自己一把
yourself in life?
有什么错
But as the upper limits are being pushed,
可是上限在逼高的同时
so are our lower limits.
下限也在被逼低呀
How many people cheat in order to get a better score
为了绩点 多少人作弊
and are eventually kicked out of school?
最终被开除
My opponent, pushing yourself
对方辩友 逼自己一把
will eventually get you in trouble.
最终是会逼出问题的呀
We're talking about how we should act
我们今天讨论的是人生
at the start of our lives.
先要如何
But what for?
请问目的何在
What is the true meaning of life?
人生的真谛到底是什么
Everyone has different
对于每个人来说
goals in life,
人生目标都是不相同的
but we have to let go
但是只有放得下
in order to find
我们才能得到
true freedom.
真正的自由
Our goals in life are different,
面对人生目标的不同
the flexibility of leaving it to fate
随缘的灵活变通
allow for the variability of people's experiences.
不套用他人的经验
Isn't it the most suitable?
难道不是最合适的吗
"Each unhappy family is unhappy in its own way,
不幸各有各的不幸
all happy families are alike".
幸福却总是相同的
Your side can't just look at the similarities,
您方不能只看相同
and not the dissimilarities.
而不看不同
Surely your side isn't pursuing
难道您方在追求的
unhappiness?
是不幸吗
All roads lead to Rome.
条条大路通罗马
Rome is Rome,
罗马都是一个罗马
but if you're in the West, you need to go East,
但你在西边就要往东走
if you're in the South you can't keep going South.
在南边就不能继续向南
The path to happiness
通往幸福的路径
depends on your situation.
要根据具体的情况而定
If you don't leave it to fate,
绝不会随缘
you might end up
只怕是离罗马
further and further away from Rome.
越走越远了
Oh my!
哎呀
I'm out of breath.
我要喘不过气来了
They're evenly matched in the free debate.
自由辩三方势均力敌
Looking at the whole competition,
结合整场的局势来看
only Teams A and C have the
就甲方和丙方
strength to contend for the first prize.
有争夺冠军的实力
Right.
没错
Team C
其中这丙方啊
has a slight edge.
还有一定的微弱优势
Let's see next if they
接下来就看他们
can consolidate their positions
能不能在结辩阶段
in the closing arguments.
巩固自己地位
So, who wins the prize…
那鹿死谁手
Depends on the closing arguments.
还看结辩
I can't see. It's blocked.
看不到了 挡着了
There are still the closing arguments.
还有结辩
We still have hope.
还有希望
But their
可是
closing argument
他们的结辩
will be made by Liu Yanze.
是刘彦泽啊
Everybody makes mistakes.
谁还没有失误
After this
经过了这一场
lively battle of words,
酣畅淋漓的唇枪舌战
next up is
下面就来到
the last section
我们本次比赛的
of the competition,
最后一个环节
closing arguments.
总结陈词
Closing arguments will begin with Team C.
总结陈词由丙方先开始
Each side has three minutes, please begin.
每方时间三分钟 有请
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
Our motion today
今天我们的持方
isn't an inspiring
既不能给大家带来
battle cry
催人奋进的呐喊
and it can't bring you
也不能给大家带来
calm in the face of defeat.
面对失败的坦然
We seem to only be able to tell everyone,
我们似乎只能告诉大家
no matter if you win or lose
无论成功还是失败
it's all down to fate.
一切随缘
Today the go-for-it side has
今天拿得起一方
been telling us to challenge,
不断地告诉我们挑战
to break through, to redefine.
去突破 去重新定义时
It makes me think that they're
让我觉得他们能够
capable of taking the Monkey King's weapon
拿起金箍棒
and sweep away the corruption of the world.
扫清天下浊
The letting-go side has
当放得下一方不断地
been telling us
告诉我们
to accept, to acknowledge,
去接受 去认同
to face the moment calmly.
去坦然面对时
It makes me think
让我觉得
they're capable of letting go of all attachments,
他们能够放下执念
and becoming a Buddha.
立地成佛
I'm confident that
我相信今天的
after today's competition,
这场比赛过后
some of you here will
在场的各位一定
choose going for it
有人选择拿起
or letting go.
或是放下
But what happens when these emotions recede?
但是当情绪退却之后呢
In the dead of night,
夜深人静时
can you really pick up a book
你真的能够拿起书本
and focus on studying
专注学习
until four in the morning?
守候凌晨四点的校园吗
Will you wake up one night
又好像午夜梦回
and be able to break ties with someone you love,
你真的能够斩断情丝
and let go of that person
放下那个陪伴你
who's been with you for so long?
许久的前任吗
For the things we go for and let go in this world,
人世间的拿起和放下
can we truly see the results
真的就在起心动念的
in the moment
一瞬间
we decide to act?
就能够得到回应吗
Have you realized?
发现了吗
Holding the Monkey King's weapon
拿得起金箍棒
doesn't mean you can sweep away the corruption of the world.
不一定能扫清天下浊
Letting go of attachments doesn't mean
放得下执念也没办法
you'll become a Buddha.
立地成佛
My fellow debaters believe that
对方辩友觉得
if you go for it, you'll succeed,
拿得起就能获得成功
if you let go, you can shuffle off this mortal coil.
放得下就能脱离苦海
But it's exactly the disappointment of life
可人生不遂人愿的地方
that we can only see
恰恰就在我们只想到了
the start,
开头
but not the results.
却没有想到结果
The bumps on the road.
那一路的坎坷
All the sufferings.
九九八十一难的磨砺
At the start,
在最初
we can't see them at all.
我们根本无法洞见
In today's competition,
今天这场比赛
we've been tantalized by verses,
金句在挑逗
brainwashed by chicken soup for the soul,
鸡汤在洗脑
encouraged by slogans.
口号在催人奋进
But our judgement has also
却也在麻痹着我们
been paralyzed.
的判断
I'm confident that among those sitting here
我相信在座的各位
there are those who can go for it
一定有人能够拿得
and let go,
起放得下
but there are certainly also those
但也一定有人拿
who can't go for it or let go.
不起放不下
Since that's the case,
既然如此
the successes reaped from going for it
拿得起的成功
are the trophies of only some,
不过是一部分人的加冕
the calm that comes from letting go
放得下的坦然
is also only the domain of
也不过是另一部分人
some of us?
的栖息
Those who chose to listen
那些选择听从
to the admonishments of Team A and B,
甲乙双方的劝诫
to chase these ends of
去追求拿起和
going for it and letting go
放下的结局
are merely using someone else's map,
不过是拿着旁人的地图
to travel in their own country.
游历自己的国度
This guide
这一本指南
leads you home
指得了你的归宿
but doesn't point out my path.
却指不了我的去路
In life there's another time, another place
人生有彼时彼地
and right now and here.
也有此时此刻
Every landscape is worthy of
每一处风景都值得我们
being treated with an
用恰如其分的
appropriate attitude.
态度去对待
But that requires us to
但这就要求我们
not make prejudgments
在遇见它之前
before we encounter it.
别做判断
That's leaving it to fate.
这就是随缘
There are many kinds of brilliant
这世界精彩的人生
lives in this world.
有许多种
But there's only one kind of desolation.
但荒凉的 只有一种
That's following other people's stories,
那就是照着别人的故事
and not living your own life.
没能过自己的一生
Thank you.
谢谢
I have the results of this competition
本次比赛的结果
right here.
已经在我手中
I'm here to announce
我来宣布
that the winner of this competition
本次比赛的获胜方是
is Dongzhou University of Finance and Economics Team!
东州财经大学代表队
Congratulation.
让我们恭喜他们
That was a great performance.
这次表现真的很不错
Your points were great.
论点很好
Alright.
好了
You guys and Team C
你们今天跟一队呀
were neck and neck today.
那是旗鼓相当啊
Besides,
再说了
this year we'll get enough experience
今年咱们把经验攒足了
and try again next year.
明年再来呗
Right?
是不是
Do you want some milk tea?
喝不喝奶茶
Hot pot?
火锅
Fried chicken?
炸鸡
Yeah?
行不
I'm fine.
我没事
I'm just a little tired.
我就是有点累了
I just need to go back to the dorm and sleep.
回寝室睡一觉就好了
Yeah.
是
You're so strong. I'm sure you're fine.
你那么强大肯定没事
If you need anything just
要有事的话就
come to the boys' dorm and get me.
来男寝找我
I know.
知道了
We did pretty well today.
今天打得是挺爽的
What a pity.
就是可惜了
Just do your best.
尽全力就好